After a whole series of content and
videos on Petri nets, now back to UML.
We have dealt with UML
for class and object diagrams, i.e.
for
static modeling.
Whereas on dynamic modeling, we've
actually had Petri nets so far,
and related concepts
reachability graphs, etc.
And then at the beginning of
the lecture the flat state diagrams, that
was also dynamic modeling, yes we also
used that to describe or model processes.
So, we have not yet looked at
dynamic aspects in these two respects with UML.
If you go back to the classifications
from the first week of the lecture and
look at what kind
of models we considered:
Under the dynamic aspects, there
was both qualitative and quantitative models.
So especially with the Petri nets
through the capacities that we looked at
last, we also have
modeling in quantitative terms.
We looked at that
for quite different examples
and have not limited it in any way
to software systems,
but especially the examples were
often somehow not necessarily software driven.
If we look at what
kind of modeling we did,
it was essentially
white box modeling.
So really capturing the
inside of the systems
that were described, by the states
or by specifying places and transitions.
That was really about
the inner workings of systems.
And in sum, with the Petri nets, it was
important to us, and that kept us busy, that we
did this relatively formally, or the Petri
nets have a formal syntax and also semantics.
In other words, they have very
fixed rules according to which they
are structured and also clear semantic
mathematical descriptions of what an execution
of a Petri net looks like
or what formal properties it has.
So that's what we've done
so far, in dynamic terms.
UML, on the other hand, we have
so far used explicitly only for static modeling.
I had once very briefly
shown a UML activity diagram
sometime at the beginning
of the Petri net chapter.
We will see that
again in a moment.
This is our introduction
to dynamic modeling with UML.
Yes, so
keyword: activity diagrams.
These are UML diagrams which,
unlike class and object diagrams, do
not describe the static
structure of a software system,
for example, but instead are
used to model flow charts, sequences
of actions, parallelism of
actions, i.e. such dynamic aspects.
Concurrency also plays
a role here.
Not on the formal level like
in Petri nets, but as an
idea that actions should
be executed independently or concurrently/parallel.
There are many applications for
activity diagrams in software design.
More generally also quite with partly
somewhat different notation, but basically corresponding to
the UML activity diagrams,
for modeling business processes,
workflows or just the case of
software modeling to describe "use cases".
So, in general, whenever
it is about summarizing
single steps in certain
typical ways to overall processes.
So, if there is a system
that performs any single steps and it
should be described which types, which
sequences of steps should be allowed.
And this of course does not correspond to
the Petri nets, where we also had a focus
on which sequences of transitions should be
allowed for a system to be modeled.
And in fact, activity diagrams are in
many ways very similar to Petri nets.
Yes we will actually
make a strong connection
by translating activity
diagrams into Petri nets.
So then will see
what the correspondence looks like.
In fact,
activity diagrams,
as is common in UML, are richer
than now this formal mechanism of Petri nets.
They provide more modeling possibilities, so
also more syntax, more different kinds
of nodes, not just places and
transitions, as in Petri nets Petri nets.
Where that was sort of a
very simple, very basic representation only.
So we'll see in a moment that
there are more elements there in activity diagrams.
The flip side is that
they don't have full formal semantics.
So some of the formal questions
that we can ask about Petri nets
and also answer unambiguously because
they are just as mathematically precise.
Will not be possible for
activity diagrams in the same way.
And it is not intended, because
activity diagrams have a descriptive character
in software modeling and should not
necessarily serve the formal analysis first.
O.k., so activity
diagrams and actually
this will first show
in simply an activity diagram.
And then play around
with that a little bit.
Again, in a separate video,
to capture, so to speak,
what can actually
be the mentioned single
steps or sequences of single
steps for this concrete activity diagram.
If we first look
at it superficially, this is
not a software example, but somehow
a house construction is to be modeled.
There is a
beginning and an end.
You can already guess that here by
the arrows and their order or direction.
And there are
single actions, such nodes.
Of course it looks a
bit like a flat state diagram.
However, we can
already see differences.
We see, for example,
that there are different
types of nodes that
will probably have different meanings.
And such special symbols
that didn't appear in our
flat state diagram at the
beginning of the lecture either.
Then there was just
nodes and arrows in between.
So here there are some special
elements, but if you look naively,
you can imagine
that there are nodes
and arrows like in
a flat state diagram.
And one carries out just
here such actions: Choose a
building site, look for an architect,
create a plan, submit a plan.
Well, and then
there are special display
elements that we haven't
seen in Petri nets yet.
And here you can already guess
that maybe something is happening in parallel.
Simply by the kind of representation and
that is of course something that did
not exist in
flat state diagrams.
There was always only
one current state and
then you moved through
the flat state diagram.
And there has to be
something more happening here somehow,
what exactly we'll look at in
a moment as we play through.
But, what I was
trying to point out was
just that there are these different types of
elements that each have a very specific role.
Which we then need to describe
when we look at activity diagrams in
more detail and then be
able to create those ourselves.